hello it is cohort two
March 8 2023
we're in meeting 19 and we're in our
second discussion on chapter eight
we will look over the questions on
chapter eight
and talk about any sections of chapter
eight
and we will
um also probably take a preview look
towards Nye
so
just at the outset does anyone have any
um comments or questions
on a
anything else that they've come across
or learned over the last week
that puts continuous time models in a
different context
any other thoughts on
continuous and discrete
or we'll look over the questions and
make sure that we've at least touched
upon each of the questions from the
previous cohorts
yeah I'll let you go for it
foreign
actually based on uh some of the claims
especially in amazing mechanics paper
and also in this recent path integrals
yeah path into girls paper
um
they they claim that
fep formulation at least from about 2012
to 2019 was largely
focused on
developing
density Over States mathematics or you
know the words the first two types of
fpp path tracking and
paths matching and path mode dynamic
split
uh I'm sorry mode matching and mode
tracking Dynamics but in recent years
they've concentrated more on developing
the path integral formulation uh I'm not
sure which direction this
textbook leans toward because in some
places it seems like it is the
tension of the previous developmental
trajectories but especially in chapter 8
it gets more into
this recent formulation of uh
formulating the path integral
mathematics but then again even in
chapter 8 we see discussions about the
previous years and this year and also
um yeah
how the textbook leans
Maps into that dichotomy
yeah thank you
good um points Thomas overviewed as such
and
this
par textbook seems to be more heavily
on the mode matching and mode tracking
however the continuous time
it's kind of like the more things change
the more they stay the same
so looking at Thomas's overview
of the um history the early
implementations as he noted
um we're in continuous time
and then in order to bring on
um
explicit planning
discrete cognitive decision making
symbolic State spaces and so on
sequential Behavior
they actually
um pivoted to the discrete time
formalism
and that that left the continuous time
lock of Volterra uh generalized
dynamical systems
uh phrasings behind
then
um
now we have a
a fusion
of the continuous and the discrete times
with uh typified by the figure 8.6
where through hierarchical nested models
we can include features of um discrete
decision making as well as continuous
perception and action
uh also discussed in live stream 46
octave does not contradict folk
psychology with kefir ramstead and Smith
which discuss essentially this model
as the folk psychological scaffold
that there's a motor active inference
layer that's perceptual and active in
continuous space and time
and then we can propose these symbolic
discrete explicit planning oriented
cognitive models
as uh Collective models I guess
so it's funny that so there's that's one
return
from the uh
earliest early 2000s continuous time
then the focused move to discrete time
and then there's the Hybrid models
and then as you pointed to it even goes
deeper because
um
the discrete time formalism is perfectly
suited for the first two phases of
Bayesian mechanics
which and the non-equilibrium steady
state and the state space
representations
whereas for the truly path tracking
Bayesian mechanics and probably G Theory
chaos and all of this
continuous time is like
your starter position
before
it even goes further afield into gauge
and the fibers and sheaths
and all of these other
formalisms
so it's almost like there's a sequence
because the discrete time and the matrix
multiplication
are very straightforward
then when we look at figure 4.3 and
figure 8.6 we kind of see some
similarities between continuous and
discrete time
and then from The Continuous time we can
take another jump into the gauge
setting
which does seem to be the the
at least in principle
the most modern representations we have
of Bayesian mechanics Michael
yeah and in figure 8.6 we have in the
top the discrete time and embedded
The Continuous time I was wondering
whether this can also be reversed
we have in the top continuous time and
then inside there we have sequences of
discrete time
so for instance if you
I mean we have a Statistics over how
long a certain
activity lasts and that can be broken
down into a sequence of several other
activities
um
could that be modeled in this way that
so for instance for this overall
activity we have we know that it takes I
don't know two minutes or 20 seconds or
so and then the next
action comes and each is broken down
into several smaller steps
that can be that are discrete
uh
can that be viewed in this way and then
how for instance if we have
a constraint over a time for instance
there we have this uh what is this Tau
one this first state which could be
maybe uh yeah if this if this was if one
of those States was was constrained by a
time and then this constraint would be
somehow handed down to the embedded
processes which Each of which could not
take longer
um then the constraint in the state
above
yeah very interesting I've never
seen that such architecture
but
it's uh in principle possible it's very
interesting and this kind of notion of
uh scheduling attentional scheduling
and time constraints
one way it might or kind of setting
where it could apply is this is again
brought up in the folk psychology paper
because the continuous time lower level
model Maps well to our uh proprioception
and muscular action and then this uh
discrete time model Maps well to
sequential explicit planning
so let's imagine it was inverted
the lower level model might be a
computer doing a dispatch
in discrete time
and the higher level is like the human
operator
and then they might also have another
discrete above them
so no need to stop at just two layers
I think it's very uh that's the exciting
Direction in question is to to build
these towers of nested models
and then lateral connections
for Collective Behavior
to
describe and specify the ecosystems of
shared intelligence so we can understand
how different
uh causal and cognitive phenomena
arise from interactions within and
across generative models
yeah
and and would there be a how could that
be modeled if if we have a temporal
constrained further down in the embedded
processes which are formulated by the
above
uh boxes or States uh it's their way to
[Music]
to notify the embedded processes that
they should stop eventually or something
like this
yeah it's uh
I mean otherwise how is this message
passed through through the only
connection is there are these matrices
which is the a matrix right
and this a matrix what they need to
determine somehow
that the embedded processes follow those
constraints
yeah yes so let's let's look at that so
uh the a matrix is the tale of two
densities
so it can be used as a recognition
density from the observations or a
generative density to generate
observations from hidden States just
looking at the top
the o
is a Markov blanket between s and V
again Mark all blankets they don't have
anything to do a priori with the Asian
environment boundary
though we can identify and construct
Markov blankets associated with agent
boundaries
this is just using Markov blanket to
mean the node or nodes
upon which two other sets of states are
conditionally independent
so the O is like the interface
it's handy it's a generative density
speaking with respect to the higher
model it's a generative density passing
observations down
to V the slowly varying causes which
modify how the derivatives are
constructed in continuous time so this
is kind of like a modifier on the Taylor
series expansion
and then
it is also um coming back up thinking
about this in a predictive processing
um like bi-directional
way
also it's changes in the continuous time
setting lower level nested model that
percolate up and modify
in a perceptual like way
higher level States so then you ask how
could constraints be modeled
there certainly could be a lot of like
engineering type Solutions
like just sort of uh for loops and
virtualization emulation
parallelization distributed
computational processes dispatch
architectures a lot of different things
like aren't
clean base graph only just in practice
you would end up implementing some of
these strategies
um but but like it's interesting to
think about well how could we really in
a principled way include time
constraints
and then
um
when the top level is discrete how how
would time constraints be achieved
and then when the top level is
continuous like you're asking about how
would time constraints be achieved
so
either way it's kind of like there's
like a window like let's just say this
is the real time
well okay here here's one more Dimension
whether or not the top or the bottom is
continuous or discrete so this could be
discrete discrete or continuous
continuous or any combination
um
one frame is real time is happening on
the top
and so this is like what we've seen in
sophisticated inference sophisticated
affective inference here's real time
this is the real simulation time
1201 1202 1203 and at each time point in
the real time
there's this
um
speculation of the past present and
future
or this can be the real-time model
in the lower model
and the higher order can be a
speculative planning
or a combination where there's a
real-time layer
that has both a faster
speculative exploitation
layer
as well as a slower nested planning
layer above real time
I think there's many
disparate
once we're in the space of nested
architectures
to capture complex cognitive phenomena
it's a really open space
which is why it's so important to have
the structured learning and the
statistical power testing and the
ability to describe and understand the
semantics of these models
because I think that they're going to
get out of control visually
very quickly
but but you're you're saying that
there's not only information going from
top to bottom but also the other way
around so the under the embedded
processes can inform the upper ones
about some outcomes
well yeah in principle so like just like
oh just only looking at the top layer o
via a could update s
or S via a could produce o
that's the Tail of Two density so
um the base graph
depending on which parameters are
established as fixed
and which ones are established as
learnable
and so on
then yes
if you allow us to be learnable
then it will learn
so that it's unsurprised about the
incoming observations of
slowly varying causes
whereas if you fix s and you only allow
V to be learnable then
etc etc
and that's like the kind of information
that's actually not shown on this graph
other than this line which we know is
missing but like as um
Toby Sinclair Smith's dissertation on
category theory has been
kind of sharing and motivating
there's actually information that's not
this is not necessary and sufficient to
replicate a full model
especially if you're going to start
talking about learning and all these
other features
this is like a um
it's a
quasi-formal
diagrammatic mnemonic
but not quite the necessary and complete
representation
but it's a super strong motivator
and helps us think about like you're a
great question about you know
continuous time on top and we should
definitely look into that and see if
those models have been used I think part
of it is people have just
um
seen a natural affinity
for continuous time models
and bodily perception bodily action
discrete time models explicit planning
so not just common commonly held
perspectives so then in that situation
it's natural to do it like this
but doesn't mean it can't be otherwise
okay
I'm not sure if these thumbs up were
from our own time last
um
okay this was I think from a from Office
hours
we talked about figure eight point five
point two
predictive coding
message passing
and 8.4
okay
generalized synchrony chaotic systems
can we
um
model that with these
predictive coding architectures
the answer is yes we can it just depends
on how you specify it
um
but that's not to say all Lorenz coupled
Lorenz attractors
are using a predictive processing
architecture nor that predictive
processing architectures acip Lorenz
attract their behavior but just you
could make a system
that happens to have both of those
features
this is another difference between
um
The Continuous and the discrete time
that I don't think we've emphasized
action is absent from equation 8.1
this is because
action is part of the generative process
not the generative model
okay
degenerative model only deals with those
variables directly influenced by States
external to a markout blanket
but those are only the sense States
and other and external states which
directly influence themselves through
latent causes
but doesn't the generative model also
include cognitive and internal States
so one could argue that the the
realization of action or the selection
of action
is part of the generative process
but can't we say that the generative
model includes planning as inference
is this
only in the case of the continuous time
I'm not sure if this is like a general
point or if this is just referring a
little bit to the different way that
action is modeled in the continuous time
setting
whereas action in the discrete setting
is modeled in this standard policy
selection
way
V are actually like not as much
even described as policies that can be
selected because it doesn't make as much
sense to talk about counterfactuals on V
they're described as just slowly varying
causes in the generative process
basically contingencies or dependencies
upon which
the Taylor series approximation
is impinged on by
that's like a very oblique way of
talking about the consequences of action
it's almost like an a differential
angle on action Michael
yeah so I'm I'm wondering whether this
Taylor series decomposition this
different different derivations that you
have there whether this is only one view
on uh on continuous time series or
whether there is also other views
that do not imply
a derivation of
decomposition of one function into
several derivations I'm not sure when I
understand this correctly
but um
but couldn't it be that
um that time constraints
are related
without derivations
I'm just wondering whether yeah one way
of seeing it are is it
the only one
yeah good question
um yeah it's not exactly a Taylor series
I think it it's though it's it's it has
Taylor series like nature because it is
dealing with successive derivative
approximations with their own
coefficients
but I think the more physics framing is
the generalized coordinates
so position
um momentum acceleration jerk
Etc
is there a way to talk about
time constraints and multiple time
scales
in continuous time
other than by taking derivatives
I mean we can definitely explore it but
like the first thought that comes to
mind is
when faced with a field of continuous
time
two approaches that are taken one of
them is to discretize time
at which point you'd be using a discrete
type model
and if you're not going to discretize
time you're going to leave it as a
smooth continuum
then a general approach is to utilize
physics-based
generalized coordinates of motion Ali
uh well yeah actually Michael
Silverstein and William Starkey
has been arguing for another approach to
formalize
cognition time
and other so-called dynamical aspects of
a system using a dynamical
mathematics so for instance in their
paper rethinking the world with neutral
monosome
removing the boundaries between mind
matter and space-time
they have proposed an alternative
approach
uh which is uh somehow uh which is
expanded uh more I mean in detail in
their beyond the dynamical universe uh
book but
um in this case they
um so very briefly they conceptualize a
system as a kind of a stationary system
that just moves from uh
um sorry that just has the first initial
position and the ending ultimate
position and we can uh by um
using this kind of a dynamical
mathematics
remove the time from the equation and
just uh
actually look at the system in a kind of
a block Universe way without actually
taking into consideration the flow of
the system through time so yeah there is
definitely other approaches to
um
model these kinds of system and even
they argue in this paper and also in
their book that this new approach can
somehow
overcome some of the long-standing
issues in
theoretical physics and or even in the
philosophy of physics
yep very um interesting this kind of
um
well writing out the the ontological
reality of time in the world is
definitely a complex topic so it's
always good to know that with these
discussions about time we're talking
about map time about like how we want to
uh model time
and in that setting
um both 8.1 and 8.2
have a um Timeless data generating
function
why observations is simply a function of
latent States on hidden States so you
know why observational States is a
function of latent States X plus some
sensor variance why
and then
there's a field
or space in which latent states have
their own flow
that is defined again without reference
to time
but as a um
derivative fields in a hamiltonian sets
so even if your Y data stream is an EEG
or fmri time series data
it's actually like
where's the time
oh where does the time go
not seeing any T's in these continuous
time models
so it's almost like we
lean so hard
into the um
continuity of time
and continuity is is at least
synonymous with or or
adjacent to differentiable
those two
are they're not exactly exactly the same
but
we work with continuous functions
because we want them to be
differentiable
we have to discretize them but the
biggest issue with discrete functions
is that they're non-differentiable
Ollie
yeah I think uh the more precise term
for uh the mathematical condition for
modeling these systems is that they need
to be in weiner spaces
so the wiener space is just a
generalizes space that contains all the
continuous and differentiable
functions and also I just wanted to
point it out that that's exactly the
point or at least one of the points of
using generalized coordinate systems in
path integral formulation of fep uh by I
mean by removing the time from
the equations
it is possible to talk about the
behavior of the system purely in terms
of their
space their the space of possible paths
instead of just looking at instead of
just following the time developmental
aspect of
um
of the particular States
awesome
yeah it's like
uh the difference between uh
putting a drop of of uh food coloring in
the cloud and tracing that one path
as it flows
and then there's definitely there's this
discussion oh should we model that one
path of the Tracer
as a path with continuous State space or
should we discretize it
and do a discrete time model of that one
realized Trace
or should we step back describe the
topology of the mountain
and then
the realized Trace
will be a path of least action on that
landscape
but we'll also be able to talk about
counterfactuals
and alternative starting conditions
initial conditions and boundary
conditions
and um
and and ask what if questions on the
landscape whereas any descriptive
historical model
will not
um
natively or simply
enable counterfactual comparisons if you
just have the path descriptor
in continuous time or in discrete time
then you don't even know what the
adjacent possibles are slash could have
been
Michael
yeah I'm I'm not sure I understand uh
this is is this possible because we
assume that the the time
goes in regular interval so if it's a
regular interval we can just ignore it
or what is the underlying
idea to abstract away from time because
time seems such a crucial kind of an
element in
all our daily lives right
yeah Ali go for it
uh well yeah it definitely is an
essential component but uh I mean the
point here is that you see so for
instance uh In classical mechanics we
have at least three different uh
formulations one is the Newtonian
mechanic formulations uh the other one
is the lagrangian and also Auditorium
formulation definitely needs uh time as
an explicit variable and parameter but
going uh from Newtonian formulation to
lagrangian and Hamilton
Ian
especially in the hamiltonian
formulation uh we can rearrange or or
derive those formulations from the
classical Newtonian formulation without
um accounting for time as an explicit
variable so time it actually implicit in
those formulations so all three of those
formulations are equivalent and they can
be recovered from each other and they
can be derived from each other but it's
just a matter of which parameters are
explicit and which are implicit so yeah
we don't
get rid of time
entirely we just use time as as a kind
of implicit parameter that doesn't need
to be explicitly defined
yeah very um just and also you said the
Assumption time is in regular intervals
but that's a discrete time model
and that's the question of
discretization of time which we're
actually like exploring in live stream
which is again not the ontological
reality of the time the time click of
the world or whatever but in modeling
spaces
um how to retain
the the elegance and the
uh analytical advantages that continuous
models provide
in terms of generalized coordinates of
motion
um physics grounded energy-based
learning
uh convergence guarantees around free
energy minimization those are all about
continuous differentiable spaces which
is why they're grounded in information
geometry and functional analysis
whereas discretization
we want to make sure that the
discretization techniques that are used
don't
um solely
or
um lose those properties of the
underlying continuous distribution
Michael
yeah I'm I'm digesting this it's a bit
so so so actually
a derivation is takes the takes the role
of time so it's only derivable because
we assume there is some kind of a
continuation or some kind of time
underlying yeah like let's let's uh pull
back to a description so if we wanted a
time this description of a car
we could describe its position at every
time and so arguably one could say well
that described like everything about
that car's trajectory what you need to
know is its position at every time
all right well you could also use the
generalized coordinates of motion
and so for each time
you could also have the car's position
in X and Y but also you could have the
car's acceleration and and and so on so
those are the derivatives of the
position
and uh it's not like extra information
like with the whole trajectory you could
recalculate the generalized coordinates
of motion from the position
but you also might want your data
structure to be that Vector at each time
step with the generalized coordinates
motion
um so you know it's here and it's going
50 kilometers an hour and it's slowing
down by two kilometers per hour per
second and its acceleration is changing
by you know
positive one kilometer per second
squared
and so on
uh another angle would be to describe
that um that space upon which there are
trajectories of the generalized
coordinates
now there's some generalized coordinates
locations that are just ridiculous like
well it's not moving at all
but its fourth derivative is super high
well any state space can be used to
describe certain points in that state
space that aren't
like feasible or
um
you know
realizable by a different physical
system obviously systems spend their
time in in
sometimes highly constrained subspaces
manifolds
of these bigger State spaces
[Music]
um
but when you describe when you say okay
well then let's make the
um generalized coordinates of motion
are fundamental State space so instead
of x y z t
as our fundamental State space
and then that is and then we're going to
derive all of our other questions from
there
it's like saying well let's have the
generalized coordinates be our state
space
but then you don't need t
of course real trajectories unfold in
quote time
pending future understandings of what
time is
but you don't need tea
in the hamiltonian
which again just to connect back to the
textbook
is that is what we're seeing in these
representations
that basically partitions signal from
noise
without explicit reference
to T as a variable
however amenable to fitting empirical
time series data
I don't think we resolved this question
about like action being in the
generative process what exactly is meant
by that
because action itself is part of the
generative process
we could say the consequences of action
or the embodiment of
but
um is this claim about regenerative
models in general or is this just saying
something about continuous time
okay precision
in our office hours last week we had
some good conversations about
precision
some on the more applied side with
perception and pain some on the more
conceptual side with the bird song
and the sensory attenuation and the role
of precision and action selection
from the perspective active inference
precision and attention are synonyms
thank you
here was the discussion from
um the office hours
so this is It's related to chapter eight
so we were talking about
um okay so in the examples first we have
just general lock of Volterra winnerless
competition
um that is then deployed in a
handwriting example
showing how lockable terra-like models
can account for sequential and reactive
Behavior
without explicit planning
so in the discrete time it'd be like I'm
here
I'm likely to go
whereas in the continuous time setting
it's just like a dynamical attractor
that doesn't have an explicit
representation of where it's going to go
in the attractor
it's just flowing in the attractor
and so then we describe the state space
of the attractor
Ali
yeah uh you're just talking about the
synonymous terms uh actually it's
interesting that marks Holmes in his
book The Hidden string spring spring
also somehow uses the word the term
Consciousness as a kind of synonym for
the Precision optimization which is one
of the Moines one of the points that
Anil Seth is strongly critical of and he
believes that we cannot simply Define uh
Consciousness as a kind of precision
optimization
and so in one of their recent papers
um
I think it was called from General to
models to generative passages a
computational approach to neural
phenomenology uh Kristen Seth and others
Max ramstead at all
actually uses
a generative model as a computational
basis for a phenomenological definition
of Consciousness which deviates
significantly from psalms's perception
uh conception of consciousness
Bob thank you yeah I haven't read this
one in depth
this day
in in the blockference
we uh
so there was there was the original
paper there was a guest stream with
Brett Kagan and Adil razi on the dish
brain
and of course the uh the sentience
fuhrer that arose
leading to
um multiple and apparently ongoing
sequences of short letters
there's a lot of interesting stuff in
here
the big contention is with the terms
active ontology sentience goal direct
Behavior embodiment uncertainty
intelligence
and their call
is
um
for glossaries
and then this paper
also
all right
come develop the glossaries
but this was just they're in the block
I'll put it in the chat as well for
people who want to see that
um
like this meta on being able to separate
the technical role
it's not just map territory but I know
we bring it up all the time and it comes
up again and again
but or maybe it is all just simply that
issue
or just something about using natural
terms
especially day-to-day terms
to refer to technical parts or outcomes
or descriptors of models
so it's all good to just accept this and
say well it's an assertion by the
authors just verbally that
uh dollar sign term one and dollar sign
term two are synonymous
that's all good to just have as a
neutral rhetorical assertion but if we
want to start latching that into our
understanding of the world then
seems like we need to
I don't know
Michael just added you to the um
document Shield accessor all right let's
um in our closing few minutes here
I think we talked about eight a fair
amount also eight is not that long
slash not that
of course one could go very deep
into
the mathematics of the continuous or the
Hybrid models but we we
um
and we could go into the other examples
and so on but
um you know
just to first pass there
okay so that is the end of chapter eight
let's just quickly in the last few
minutes look ahead to nine
just because we have the best Hammer
does not mean that every problem is a
nail
models are useful if they can answer
scientific questions
chapter 9 focuses on active inference in
the context of empirical data
section 9.2 is on metabayesian methods
and it's going to talk about the setting
of cognitive modeling with active
inference in the setting of Behavioral
or ethological experimentation
and so it's not just going to be a proof
of principle like we constructed a t
Maze and a simulated rat
um
there's two reasons to fit a
computational model to observed Behavior
the first reason is to estimate
parameters of Interest
the second reason is to compare
alternative hypotheses
they recap base theorem and they're
going to be discussing Bayes theorem in
the context of scientists scientific
epistemology
and a really Bayesian epistemology
as the behavioral investigator
that lends itself to this key figure 9.1
that characterizes the metabasian view
so in the inner dashed box we have the
cognitive model that we're constructing
of the ant
so map territory level one
then we're in our own dashed box
because we are providing what for us our
action selections and parameters of the
experiment drawn from distributions of
experiments and stimuli
and presenting it to the ant
then potentially with errors and
variance Etc observing Behavior so this
is the metabasian view view from the
outside
and viewed from the inside now there is
a view from the inside
but this is a map of the view of the
inside
and this is our schema of our control
framework from the outside
so all the talking about sweeping over
families of cognitive models of ants and
rats and stuff like that that's all
happening in this dashed box but in the
outer loop
um we are exploring different maximally
informative cognitive modeling settings
and observations to observe
and again like the imperative being
maximally informative information
through experiments not some kind of
falsificationist
accept or reject dialectic but putting
it more into a base Factor
continuous
juxtaposition of portfolios of
hypotheses rather than like a p-value
frequentist except a reject framework
um
it's going to be like
of active inference
in multiple ways
okay turn away from that sort of
ethological view to some technical
details on the variational LaPlace
um
section 9.4 parametric empirical Bays
PEB is a way that you can start with a
real data set and kind of use the first
instantiation of the whole data set or
part of the data set to jump start you
or like
um parachute drop you into a reasonable
area of phase space
and that facilitates expectation
maximization type algorithms and
empirical applications of Bayesian
statistics like we're going to fit our
prior on this fifth grade classroom's
Heights from
a bigger data set of heights that were
collected from first through eighth
grade and that's going to be our prior
for this fifth grade classroom or we're
just going to take the measurements we
did get
and then summary statistics of that
distribution we're going to use as our
prior
then 9.5 it's kind of like a little bit
like a chapter six a recipe but here the
recipe is about collecting data
formulating a model
as in chapter 7 or in chapter six if you
want to pull back even more generally
specify likelihood priors solve for
probabilities and evidences and then
perform statistical analyzes and that's
actually where descriptive statistics
can come into play like we did in Anova
on these cognitive modeling parameters
and then they have a um summary figure
9.2
so here we're like really bringing
together a lot of sections of the book
in slide one is the teammates
here's the generative process and
generative model that could have been
written before
Blends the likelihood function that
allows this invertible model such that
you can use the generative model to
generate synthetic data or you can take
data of that structure and do
statistical inference on so we did five
conditions and it turns out condition
four and five with this p-value are
significantly higher or this base Factor
than there
and some examples of generative models
some models of false inference a long
table
in a summary
all right
thank you
that
um concludes chapter 8 will return in
one minute or two minutes with um
beginning of uh next door thank you